Hi.
And welcome back to another ElectroBOOM 101.
This time is about AC and DC.
Oh, you think it's very straightforward, eh?
DC is this straight line
...and AC is this wiggly line?
Well, you know nothing!
Although
...it's not... super inaccurate,
...but I can't finish the video now!
[police sirens]
Bwah.
It could use some echo.
I put some complex-looking formulas
on my videos to look smart,
...in case some professor or something is watching.
...but frankly, in my line of work,
...I use the simple stuff to design complex circuits.
I want you to GRASP the meaning
of what I'm trying to say
...and really FEEL it in your heart.
And don't bother with formulas too much.
I talked to you about what voltage
and current are in the past video,
...that the current
...is the amount of flowing charges per second,
(mainly electrons in a wire)
...and voltage
...is the available energy per unit charge,
...that moves charges and creates current.
Stop saying:
Okay!?
Now, like water in a river,
...the charges can flow steadily, without any change.
It's called DC, or direct current.
In DC, there is absolutely no change
...in the speed of flowing currents.
No ripples.
Nothing.
Steady as a beating drum.
Oh.
Beating drum is AC.
That's DC. Nothing to it.
It's the AC, or alternating current,
...that's the mother of all evil.
That's when the flowing charges
...change direction and go back and forth
...with an alternating pattern,
...which can be anything!
Of course, as long as it's changing forward in time.
It can't return in time.
Time travel is impossible.
If you disagree,
...return in time,
...find me yesterday,
...and punch me in the eyebrow!
Now, the most basic alternating waveform
...is a sinusoidal waveform,
...or sine wave,
...which looks like this:
Imagine you have a circle with a radius of one,
...and a dot that's moving around
its perimeter at a fixed speed.
Now if you look at the shadow
of the dot on the vertical axis
...and plot it in time,
...you will have a sine wave with a magnitude of 1.
And as you all know,
...the city voltage is a sine wave.
Now, if we scope it-
Um...
Which one was the live wire?
Black is grou-
[REDACTED]
Argh.
White is neutral!
Black is the color of a pirate flag.
Black dangerous!
Here is our 120 volt AC.
The period of an AC signal
...is the time it takes for one full pattern to finish,
...which in this case is 16.7 milliseconds (ms).
And the frequency is the number of times
...this pattern repeats in 1 second,
...which is 60 hertz in this case.
So naturally,
...frequency, shown with the lowercase 'f',
...with a unit of hertz (Hz),
...is equal to 1 over period,
...which is shown with a capital 'T',
...with a unit of second (sec or s).
The sine is shown as:
...of Alpha (α)
...that gives you the value of sin between ±1.
And alpha (α) is the angle of where your dot is,
...which is typically in radian scale,
...where 360 degrees (°) is equal to 2 pi (π) radians.
Now for a proper sine wave formula, we have
...A (amplitude) times
sine of [ωt (Omega times time) plus φ (Phi)].
Like I said, a sine formula gives you a magnitude of 1.
So, for example, if you want to show a 100 volt signal
...A (amplitude) would be equal to 100.
For now, let's assume Phi (φ) is 0.
Omega (ω) is called the angular frequency,
...and shows how fast your signal will oscillate.
And t is time in seconds.
Now, as the time passes,
...the angle changes from 0 to 360 degrees and forward.
But if Omega (ω) is bigger,
...the change of angle per time (t) is faster,
...and so higher frequency.
Omega (ω) is defined as
...2 times pi (π) times f (for frequency).
So for example, if frequency is equal to 1 hertz,
...we have this formula.
If time starts at 0 seconds,
...we start at 0 degrees (°),
...and when time reaches 1 second,
...we reach 2 pi (π) or 360 degrees (°),
...which means we have turned 1 turn in 1 second,
...or 1 hertz.
You know what they say about AC?
[beautiful laughter]
Now, Phi (φ)
...is just a fixed angle we add here.
Without Phi (φ), we always start at zero,
...but with Phi (φ) we can shift our waveform.
For example, in case of three-phase line,
...we have one phase that starts at zero,
...the other one that's shifted 120 degrees (°),
...like this,
...and the third one that's shifted -120 degrees (°),
...like this.
They also call phi (φ) "phase-shift."
All these formulas shown is that how the flow of current
...moves one way, slows down, and returns.
Or in terms of voltage,
...how the voltage changes in time,
...like you saw on the scope.
Wake up! [very gentle slap]
There are still things to talk about here!
And you thought that's all there is about AC?
No, that was just a sine wave!
We have so many different AC patterns,
...like:
...or anything in between.
Now, let me tell you a fascinating secret
...that only the engineers know.
[whispering] You're not gonna find a job anyways,
...so learn and do what you love very well!
[speaking normally] And the second thing is that
...any periodic wave form
...can be written as the sum of a series of sine waves
...with different magnitudes and frequencies.
Any wave form.
Here, I put a spreadsheet together for you
...to add a series of sine waves
...and see what wave form we get.
This one is for the triangular wave form,
...with a specific series formula.
What you see here is the main sine wave.
If I add the next sine wave in the series,
...we get this.
And then the next one,
...next one, next one, next one,
...next one, next one...
It looks very much like a triangular wave.
If I was able to go to infinity,
...it would be a perfect triangular waveform.
For the square wave,
...we have a different series formula.
And again, I start from the main sine wave
...and add the next one.
And next one,
...next one, next one, next one,
...next one, next one, next one, next one.
And the more I can add,
...the more square it gets.
And here is the one for the sawtooth.
And I add a...
...next one, next one, next one,
[ˢᵒ ᵐᵃⁿʸ 'ᴺᵉˣᵗ ᵒⁿᵉˢ' ᵗʰᵃᵗ ᵗʰᵉ ᶜᵃᵖᵗⁱᵒⁿᵉʳ ʰᵃˢ ᵍⁱᵛᵉⁿ ᵘᵖ]
And that's as far as I like to go.
They call all these sine waves
that create a specific waveform
..."harmonics",
...with the main harmonic being
the lowest frequency sine wave.
Like for example, my voice has a
[starts speaking with melody]
...main frequency that can be the same as yours,
...but my voice is different than yoooours
[speaking normally] ...because my harmonics
...that are made by vibrations and resonances
...through my own skull cavities and bones
...are different than yours.
Now, thankfully,
...if your voice is garbage,
...it doesn't mean that you have an ugly face too.
It's just that your harmonics are
[REDACTED]
Similarly, all these waveforms
...can have the same main harmonic
at the same frequency.
But their other harmonics are different.
Now, you could refer to all these
waveforms by their magnitude,
...like a 1 volt peak sine wave or a square wave,
...but it's kind of meaningless in
terms of electronic power delivery.
Because, for example, a 1 volt peak sine wave
...delivers a different power than a
square wave or a triangular wave.
That's why for power lines,
...instead of using the peak voltage or current, we use:
For example, a 1 volt RMS AC
...delivers the same power as a 1 volt DC
...over a 1 ohm resistor.
That's why for the city power lines,
...the 120 volt AC or 240 volt AC are the RMS values.
For sine waves,
...the peak value (Vₚₑₐₖ) is equal to
...the RMS value (Vᵣₘₛ) times square root of 2 (√2)
But let's take a look at my car inverter,
...which converts the 12 volts
off the car to 120 volts AC.
And right now, it's running on my 12-volt battery.
If I probe it...
Um...
Does it matter which wire I connect to?
Nope,
...because it's not connected to the mains anymore.
So...
...there we go.
See, this is the waveform that
my inverter is outputting,
...and my meter,
...if you can see,
...still reads around 120 volt AC RMS,
...although the
...peak of this waveform is only around 140 volts,
...compared to the peak of the sine wave,
...which was 170 volts.
This waveform, or the city sine wave,
...or just the 120 volt DC,
...can output the same power over the same resistor
...because their RMS values are the same.
Of course, the RMS of DC is the same as the DC value.
Now, we are pretty much done with AC.
But wait, there's more!
We don't have just AC or just DC.
In fact, in almost all cases,
...we have some of both added.
An AC waveform, like this,
...can have a DC added to it,
...like this,
...that just...
...shifts it up and down.
It's like adding a fixed number to the AC wave.
Now when you add the AC and DC together,
...the total RMS
...is NOT the sum of the AC RMS plus the DC value.
It was a mistake I made a while back.
Made a bunch of smoke.
The total RMS is-
Uh, how do you read this?
It is the
...square root (√) of the AC RMS (Vₐ꜀ ᵣₘₛ)
squared (²) plus the DC squared (²).
Eh.
Whatever. I'm done.
But wait, there's more!
Let me give you a general idea
of what DC and AC are good for.
DC is a constant.
It's ideal for power delivery to things like
...circuits
...or lights
...or DC motors and such,
...or to set or bias a circuit in a known state.
But AC,
...it is also great for power delivery.
It is needed for power conversion.
It can carry valuable information.
It can transfer power or information over wire or air.
It is used for computing complex information.
AC is the base of every technology out there,
...while DC is powering them.
Yep, now we're really done.
RECESS!
[beatboxing and dancing]
[holy unibrow dance]
Subtitles/captions by Jonathan Lee (Pentameron)
youtube.com/c/PentameronSV